
🔍 Problem Summary

"Signature required" during SAML Single Logout (SLO) initiated by the Service Provider (SP).

Although the LogoutRequest appears to include a <Signature> element, the IdP (PingFederate) rejects it, saying the signature is not present.

🔬 Diagnosis & Root Cause
The LogoutRequest uses HTTP-Redirect binding, which is a special case in SAML.

According to the SAML Bindings specification (section 3.4.4.1(https://docs.oasis-open.org/security/saml/v2.0/saml-bindings-2.0-os.pdf)), when using Redirect binding, the signature MUST NOT be embedded inside the XML like in a typical POST binding.

Instead, the signature must be:

Base64-encoded

Passed as a query parameter named Signature in the URL

Accompanied by a SigAlg parameter

Even though the LogoutRequest XML has a <ds:Signature> tag, PingFederate does not look for it there when using Redirect binding. It expects the signature in the URL query string.

🔴 Mismatch: The SP sends the signature in the XML instead of in the URL, so PingFederate sees it as "missing", triggering the Signature required error.



✅ Solution
Option 1: Fix the SP’s Redirect Signature Implementation
Make sure the SP implements SAML Redirect binding signatures properly:

Use query string parameters:

SAMLRequest

RelayState (optional)

SigAlg

Signature

Sign the URL string as per SAML Bindings Section 3.4.4.1

This is the preferred and standards-compliant fix.

Option 2: Switch to HTTP-POST Binding
If the SP can't correctly implement Redirect signatures, you can:

Reconfigure the SP and IdP to use HTTP-POST binding instead

POST binding allows the signature to be embedded in the XML body using <ds:Signature>



=======================================================================================================

The correct form of a LogoutRequest over the Redirect binding is (as seen from the PingFederate server.log):

REQUEST (GET) from 127.0.0.1: ---PARAMETERS---
SigAlg:
http://www.w3.org/2000/09/xmldsig#rsa-sha1
SAMLRequest:
fZJdb4IwFIb/Cuk935PMRkjM0IUEZxQ3F29MhaKd0FZO8WO/foBLZha3m140z/u8PScdACkLiWOxFbWa00NNQWlhczBOFBPcRzulJGDTLERKip0AhfuWa5ssk2YST4027yAtAqhpxEERrnzkWLarW57ueAvHxb0HbLmG5T2uGi70Ud7X4/XsfZJY8Yiv9tNDtYzneb5djzZIe6MVdL2OYSHtXBYccNvho7riWBBggDkpKWCV4mQ4iXEDYgJAq/a9txH5f0ZWQolUFCgYtDTuRqiCnzkzmpO6UJhyxdQlygbmLXcNvTTaKNTGoiqJ+rvPNuzuhmV63qG45iBpynJGMxR8iB3/tl+FV7vECYV2GxHP6DmQp4tYH+3PeXIiujtmZGTHzwWD5at7Df/i7zmGT7M0CzfpabFfeoaMxbTHHEHpsf+Hw7zzQYIv
RelayState:
di4n4KQMLyEhBjppRsSkig7BiqR9vd
Signature:
i0sTmzp6Dd2/M8n0Y3EzGdQstemeG+TdD4jQ0bZ6F8O8aMGeH6EHKq0fWVDJADiRa+kNOfdfR9dazKNxX6EkesmJLlAw5sCo2VY6VXCkZvuEU7474N8MKHRTHQCIZlrMmUgxtqwPzBHouXu19+AOVbbZy7im45aczWipTa06Axk=